A Guide to the Robinson Family Papers, 1684-1915
John D. Rockefeller, Jr. Library, Colonial Williamsburg Foundation
John D. Rockefeller, Jr. Library, Colonial Williamsburg
Robinson Family Papers, 1684-1915.
John D. Rockefeller, Jr. Library, Colonial Williamsburg Foundation
MS 94.6
2 volumes.
Robinson Family.
Administrative Information
Access
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Purchase, 1994.
Biographical/Historical Information
Christopher Robinson arrived in Virginia, from England, in approximately 1668. He quickly established himself at a plantation called "Hewick," named after his family's Hewick estate in England. Descendants of Christopher Robinson soon became influential landholders, tobacco traders, and political leaders in the colony. Christopher Robinson's great-grandson, Christopher IV, took the side of the Crown during the American Revolution, accepting a captain's position with the Queen's Rangers. After Britain's defeat in America, Christopher of the Queen's Rangers relocated to Canada where he served the royal government in various capacities. Charles W. Robinson descended from this "Hewick" line of the Robinson family. In addition to members of the Robinson family, notable names discussed in the collection of documents include: Richard Corbin, Ralph Wormeley, Albert W. Woods, H. Farnham Burke, Lyon G. Tyler, Letitia Cornwallis, J. H. Coombe, Thomas Jefferson, King George III, General Robert Porteus, John Maynard, Edmund Pendleton, John Graves Simcoe, Robert Rogers, "Mr. Dinwiddie," John Wentworth, Fletcher Norton, and George Wythe.
Scope and Content Information
Original seventeenth, eighteenth, nineteenth, and early twentieth-century manuscripts, official documents, sketches, and photographs, as well as copies of original letters and documents relating to Charles W. Robinson and his ancestors. The bulk of the material relates to Charles W. Robinson's efforts to trace and register his family pedigree with London's Herald's College.
Arrangement
All items are bound in two volumes, Original Family Papers Virginia and Canada 1684-1798 and Family History Papers I: Records, Wills, Lawsuits, Herald's College Correspondence, etc., with board covers accented with leather bindings.
Index Terms
Family Names:
Robinson family.
Persons:
Burke, H. Farnham (Henry Farnham), 1859-1930.; Corbin, Richard, ca. 1708-1790.; Cornwallis, Letitia.; Coombe, J. H.; Maynard, John.; Norton, Fletcher, 1716-1789.; Pendleton, Edmund, 1721-1803.; Porteus, Robert.; Rogers, Robert, 1731-1795.; Simcoe, John Graves, 1752-1806.; Tyler, Lyon Gardiner, 1853-1935.; Wentworth, John.; Woods, Albert W.; Wormeley, Ralph.; Wythe, George, 1726-1806
Subjects:
American loyalists--Canada.
Corporate Names:
Queen's Rangers, 1776-1781.
Geographical Names:
United States--History--Revolution, 1775-1781.; Virginia-- Genealogy.
Contents List
- Family history papers: records, wills, lawsuits, Herald's College correspondence, etc. (Volume I)
  - Copy of a pedigree, 1913. (Page 9-15)
    John Robinson and descendants from 1712. Copy made by C.W. Robinson in 1913.
  - Pedigree, 10 August 1854. (Page 18-23)
    Robinson family genealogy 1495-1854. Signed by Albert Woods, Herald's College, London.
  - Pedigree. (Page 25)
    Written description by C.W. Robinson of Robinson family genealogy on pages 18-23.
  - Copy of a memorandum, 1913. (Page 27-31)
    Colonel Beverley Robinson and descendants through 1748. Original by Frederick Robinson, 1838. Copy by C.W. Robinson, 1913.
  - Colonel Bruce, Government House, to Chief Justice John Beverley Robinson, 2 April 1850. (Page 35-38)
    Concerns modifications to the statutes of the Order of the Bath.
  - Albert Woods, Heralds College, London, to John Beverley Robinson, 26 November 1850. (Page 39)
    Warrant issuing John Beverley Robinson as Companion of the Most Honorable Order of the Bath.
  - Albert Woods, Heralds College, London, to John Beverley Robinson, Canada West, 27 November 1850. (Page 40)
    Concerns the one pound fee for appointment to the Order of the Bath.
  - Albert Woods, Heralds College, London, to John Beverley Robinson, 29 November 1850. (Page 41-42)
    Enclosure of ribbon and badge for the Order of the Bath.
  - John Beverley Robinson to Albert Woods, 3 January 1851. (Page 43-44)
    Concerns the Order of the Bath.
  - Copy of the will of Bishop John Robinson of London, March 1722. (Page 47-52)
    All goods and wealth given to Emma Robinson, wife and executrix of will, with certain stipulations for distribution among various persons.
  - Albert Woods, London, to Captain L. Robinson, 19 February 1851. (Page 57-58)
    Concerns a sketch of the Robinson family crest.
  - Pedigree. (Page 59)
    Robinson family genealogy concerning evolution of the family crest.
  - Pedigree. (Page 60-61)
    Robinson family since 1755 with memorandum of explanation by C.W. Robinson.
  - Memorandum of John Beverley Robinson. (Page 63-64)
    Concerns Christopher Robinson and Colonel Beverley Robinson.
  - John Beverley Robinson to Mary Proper, 3 February 1853. (Page 65-68)
    Copy of a letter concerning the genealogy of the Robinson family.
  - Virginia Gazette article, 28 July 1768. (Page 71)
    Concerns the death of Christopher Robinson.
  - Virginia Gazette article, 17 March 1747. (Page 72)
    Concerns the death of the wife of Christopher Robinson. Postscript by Richard Randolph.
  - Copies of court records. (Page 75-77)
    Concerns Robinson family court cases from 1784-1787 with notes by C.W. Robinson.
  - C. Robinson, Richmond, to J.B. Robinson, Toronto, 16 April 1853. (Page 78-80)
    Concerns copies of court records about John and Christopher Robinson.
  - Copy of a petition of Richard Corbin and Ralph Wormeley, 1769. (Page 84-95)
    Concerns the estate of Christopher Robinson.
  - Copies of court records, 1784-1789. (Page 98-135)
    Concerns the estate of Christopher Robinson from the High Court of Chancery, Virginia.
  - Copy of court records, 1785-1789. (Page 138-157)
    Concerns John Robinson and Richard Corbin, executor of estate of Christopher Robinson from the High Court of Chancery, Virginia.
  - Copy of the will of Christopher Robinson, 16 July 1768. (Page 165-168)
    Wills his estate to Christopher Benjamin (son) with one-third to wife Sarah and portion of land to daughters Mary and Betty.
  - Copy of Sarah Robinson's will, 6 December 1771. (Page 169-172)
    Richard Corbin and Ralph Wormeley named executors of late husband's estate (Christopher Robinson) with slaves given to Christopher (son) and Elizabeth (daughter).
  - Copy of the will of Christopher Robinson, 19 October 1775. (Page 173-174)
    Richard Corbin and Ralph Wormeley named executors with all personal property given to Elizabeth Robinson (sister).
  - Copy of an Act of Parliament, 1772. (Page 179-210)
    Concerns the sale of the estate of Christopher Robinson in England known as Hewick.
  - Lord Seaton to Duke of Newcastle, 27 May 1854. (Page 215-221)
    Concerns the distinguished service of Chief Justice John Beverley Robinson. Reply by Duke of Newcastle added to end.
  - Duke of Newcastle, Downing Street, London, to Lord Seaton, 17 June 1854. (Page 222-223)
    Public recognition of Chief Justice John Beverley Robinson's distinguished public service.
  - Lord Seaton to Captain Lepoy, 19 June 1854. (Page 224-225.)
    Concerns public recognition of Chief Justice John Beverley Robinson.
  - Lord Elgin to Captain Lepoy, 4 July 1854. (Page 226-227)
  - J.H. Lepoy, Woodrich Common, to George Grey, 4 August 1854. (Page 228-229)
    Concerns a baronetage to be conferred on the late Chief Justice John Beverley Robinson.
  - Albert Woods, Herald's College, London, to Captain Lepoy, 4 August 1854. (Page 232-233)
    Concerns the pedigree of Chief Justice John Beverley Robinson for conferring and registering a Baronet in his name.
  - Albert Woods, Herald's College, London, to Captain Lepoy, 10 August 1854. (Page 235-237)
    Concerns the patent for Baronet of Chief Justice Beverley Robinson.
  - Albert Woods, Herald's College, London, to Chief Justice Robinson's estate, 11 August 1854. (Page 239-241)
    Concerns arms of pedigree and conferring title of a baronet.
  - Albert Woods, Herald's College, London, to Captain Lepoy, 12 August 1854. (Page 242-243)
    Request for documentation of Chief Justice Robinson's pedigree.
  - Albert Woods, Herald's College, London, to Captain Lepoy, 16 August 1854. (Page 244-245)
    Concerns the establishment of John Beverley Robinson's official title as "Chief Justice for Canada West."
  - Albert Woods, Herald's College London, to Captain Lepoy, 21 August 1854. (Page 246)
    Concerns a visit to the Colonial Office and sketch of Robinson Family Arms and Crest.
  - Albert Woods, Herald's College, London, to Captain Lepoy, 25 August 1854. (Page 248-249)
    Concerns the formalization of Chief Justice John Beverley Robinson's title and request for 78 pound payment for the Patent of Baronetage.
  - Albert Woods, Herald's College, London, to Captain Lepoy, 28 August 1854. (Page 250-251)
    Concerns receipt of payment for Patent of Baronetage and formal announcement in "the Gazette."
  - Albert Woods, Herald's College, London, to Captain Lepoy, 2 September 1854. (Page 252-254)
    Outline of Robinson family pedigree and request for corrections.
  - H.J. Kuyoett, Home Office, London, to Captain Lepoy, 19 October 1854. (Page 255-258)
    Concerns the baronetage of John Beverley Robinson.
  - Albert Woods, Herald's College, London, to Captain Lepoy, 30 October 1854. (Page 258)
    Concerns a patent assigning Arms and Crest of Robinson family.
  - Memorandum. (Page 259-261)
    Concerns fees to create and patent a baronetage for John Beverley Robinson totaling 350 pounds.
  - Letter, 3 April 1855. (Page 263-267)
    Concerns an incorrect pedigree of the Robinson family printed in The Yorkshireian in England. A clipping of the article is included.
  - Albert Woods, Herald's College, London, to Sir J. Beverley Robinson, 19 April 1855. (Page 269)
    Concerns an article to be printed in Burke's edition of "Peerage and Baronetage."
  - Albert Woods, Herald's College, London, to John Beverley Robinson, 21 April 1855. (Page 270-271)
    Approval of Burke's article.
  - John Beverley Robinson (?) to Albert Woods, 28 April 1855. (Page 271)
    Concerns Robinson family pedigree. A letter of 3 March 1875 from Albert Woods to Major C.W. Robinson is attached.
  - John Beverley Robinson, New Brunswick, to John Beverley Robinson, 10 February 1857. (Page 273-278)
    Family pedigree with enclosed copy of 1781 letter concerning Christopher Robinson of the Queen's Rangers.
  - R. Brock, Richmond, to C.W. Robinson, 21 March 1881. (Page 279-285)
    Concerns the pedigree of the Robinsons of Hewick printed in the Richmond Standard. Article enclosed.
  - H. Farnham Burke, Somerset Herald, to C. W. Robinson, 10 August 1901. (Page 287)
    Concerns fees for compilation and recording of Robinson Family pedigree.
  - C.W. Robinson to H. Farnham Burke, Somerset Herald, 16 August 1901. (Page 287-288)
    Requests reply concerning recording of family pedigree.
  - H. Farnham Burke, Herald's College, London, to C.W. Robinson, 17 August 1901. (Page 288)
    Concerns evidence establishing C.W.R.'s descent and right to the Robinson family coat of arms.
  - H. Farnham Burke, Herald's College, London, to C.W. Robinson, Linfield, 21 August 1901. (Page 288)
    Enclosing payment for registration of pedigree.
  - Notes on sources, 8 August 1901. (Page 290-292)
    List of documents submitted to Herald's College to support C.W. Robinson's application for pedigree.
  - F. Beverley, Spotsylvania Court House, to C.W. Robinson, 21 January 1871. (Page 293-294)
    Has no new information but is working on the "Weasley" estate request.
  - Booklet, c. 1842. (Page unnumbered)
    Forty page book by Lady Robinson containing family history.
  - Court notice, 1875. (Page 297)
    Gloucester and Hanover Court Houses notifying that records for 1733-1792 destroyed by fire and during the Civil War.
  - A.S. Scott-Gatty Garter, College of Arms, to C.W. Robinson, 27 February 1905. (Page 301)
    Concerns the rejection of an application for Robinson Pedigree and Arms.
  - Pedigree notice, 22 February 1905. (Page 303)
    Charles H. Athill and T.M.J. Watkin decide there is insufficient evidence of certain family relations in the Robinson family genealogy.
  - Copy of a deed, 3 November 1763. (Page 309-310)
    Deed for the sale of 1190 acres of land in Spotsylvania County from William Robinson to John Robinson (son).
  - Lizzie M. Robinson, Washington, D.C. to "My Dear Cousin" (C.W. Robinson?), 11 May 1909. (Page 317-336)
    Concerns family genealogy and errors found by Herald's College. Enclosing possible corrections including information obtained from the Parish Register of Christ Church, Middlesex County, Virginia.
  - Lyon G. Tyler, College of William and Mary, Williamsburg, Virginia to C.W. Robinson, 22 May 1908. (Page 337-338)
    Concerns corrections in the family genealogy.
  - H.F. Burke, Herald's College, London, to C.W. Robinson, Ealing, 24 November 1910. (Page 340)
    Concerns approval of Robinson family pedigree.
  - C.W. Robinson, Ealing, to H. Farnham Burke, Heralds College, London, 14 July 1910. (Page 345-356)
    Concernst the application to Herald's College for Robinson family pedigree.
  - Copy of the will of John Robinson of Middlesex County, Virginia, 21 February 1785. (Page 368-371)
    Leaves home and plantation to daughters Judith, Mary, and Priscilla until death or marriage when it is passed to William (J.R.'s son). Son John receives "Green Branch", daughters Katherine and Mary and son Peter receive slaves. Other family members receive money, livestock, etc. Copy dated 4 May 1853.
  - Extract from "Leighs Virginia Reports," (Page 372)
    Concerns Robert Robinson, son of John Robinson, Middlesex County, Virginia.
  - Copy of a letter from Christopher Robinson, Kingston, Upper Canada, to Robert Robertson, 6 July 1793. (Page 373-375)
    Concerns his recent appointment to government service. Copy dated 28 August 1893.
  - Letter from Western Telegraph Company, New York, to John Robinson, 26 January 1870. (Page 377-378)
    Concerns family research.
  - Copy of a letter from Charles Robinson, Urbanna, to Richard Corbin, 4 August 1767. (Page 379)
    Concerns money owed to Peter Robinson's estate by Charles Robinson.
  - Copy of a letter from P.W. Clarborin, 21 June 1769. (Page 379)
    Concerns Peter Robinson's estate.
  - T.M. Robinson to C.W. Robinson, 2 May 1909. (Page 381-393)
    Concerns family pedigree research and current family news.
  - Lyon G. Tyler, College of William and Mary, Williamsburg, Virginia, to C.W. Robinson, Ealing, 13 March 1909. (Page 396)
    Concerns family pedigree research. Enclosed is a chancery suit document about Peter Robinson.
  - Copy of chancery suit, 13 June 1791. (Page 389-400)
    Concerns the estate of Peter Robinson, deceased, George Wythe presiding judge.
  - Lyon G, Tyler, College of William and Mary, Williamsburg, Virginia, to C.W. Robinson, London, 16 April 1909. (Page 401)
    Concerns family pedigree research. Enclosing documents about Peter Robinson.
  - Court Scheduled (copy), July 1802. (Page 402)
    Chancery suits involving Grymes v. Robinson 1792-1802.
  - Copy of a petition. (Page 403-408)
    Grymes v. Robinson concerning the execution of the will of Peter Robinson.
  - Copy of a petition, 29 August 1792. (Page 409-410)
  - Copy of accounts, 1765-1773. (Page 411-412)
    Accounts of the estate of Peter Robinson, entered into the Court of Middlesex County 29 August 1792.
  - Lyon G. Tyler, College of William and Mary, Williamsburg, Virginia, to C.W. Robinson, Ealing, 14 October 1909. (Page 413-414)
    Concerns family pedigree research.
  - Lyon G. Tyler, College of William and Mary, Williamsburg, Virginia, to C.W. Robinson, Ealing, 7 February 1910. (Page 415-416)
  - Article from William and Mary Quarterly, Volume XVII, No. 3, January 1910, pages 181-194 (Page 417-432)
    Concerns the genealogy of the Virginia branch of the Robinson family.
  - W.G. Standard, Virginia Historical Society, to C.W. Robinson, Ealing, 25 February 1910. (Page 433-434)
    Concerns Robinson family genealogy.
  - J. Beverley Robinson, New York, to C.W. Robinson, 8 February 1910. (Page 435-436)
    Concerns family pedigree research about relationship of Peter and Christopher Robinson.
  - J. Beverley Robinson, Edgewater, New Jersey, to C.W. Robinson, 8 February 1910. (Page 437-439)
    Concerns family pedigree research about the relationship of Peter and Christopher Robinson.
  - Newspaper article from the Richmond Standard, 16 April 1881. (Page 441-442)
    Concerns births, deaths, and marriages of members of the Robinson family as found in the parish register of Middlesex County, Virginia
  - Copy of a marriage license, 9 August 1750. (Page 443)
    Bond issued in Middlesex County, Virginia for the marriage of Peter Robinson and Sarah Lester. Copy dated 13 July 1910.
  - "Alumni Quncersis" (copy of excerpt), 1888. (Page 445-446)
    Virginia Robinsons genealogy 1715-1886.
  - G.H. Sterling, Maugerville, New Brunswick, to C.W. Robinson, 27 November 1879. (Page 447-449)
    Lack of information about Robinson family genealogy as St. John's(?) parish register destroyed by fire.
  - Copy of registry records, 1784-1786. (Page 452-454)
    Robinson family entries found in the record books of the Registry Office of St. John's, New Brunswick.
  - Memorandum of C.W. Robinson, 14 July 1910. (Page 456)
    Concerns the family of Esther (Sayre) Robinson.
  - Copy of a letter from Colonel Beverley Robinson to "My Dear Daughter," 3 July 1784. (Page 457-460)
    Family news. Copy dated December 1879.
  - Copy of a letter from John Robinson, Virginia, to Robert Robinson, New York, 9 June 1783. (Page 461-462)
    Concerns Captain Wormeley's loyalty to the British government, payment for slaves taken in the war, and financial matters. Copy dated November 1879.
  - Copy of a letter from John Robinson, Virginia, to Robert Robinson, Nova Scotia, 15 June 1784. (Page 463-464)
    Concerns the Virginia Assembly, return of South Carolinian loyalists to their estates. Copy dated November 1879.
  - Fragments (Page 465)
    Concern Christopher Robinson of the Queen's Rangers from Gloucester County, Virginia.
  - Lyon G. Tyler, College of William and Mary, Williamsburg, Virginia, to C.W. Robinson, Ealing, 2 November 1911. (Page 467-468)
    Concerns family pedigree research, Robinson legal suits and all old Chancery papers destroyed in Court House fire.
  - Lyon G. Tyler, College of William and Mary, Williamsburg, Virginia, to C.W. Robinson, Ealing, 8 April 1914. (Page unnumbered)
    Request for copies of the wills of Peter Robinson (1765) and Judith Robinson (1774) previously destroyed in Court House fire.
  - Notes, 1913. (Page 469)
    C.W. Robinson's introduction to a section on the "Crossthwaithe" Robinsons.
  - Notes. (Page 473-478)
    C.W. Robinson's interpretation of family pedigree 1589-1712 with detailed information about dates of births, deaths, and marriages.
  - Copy of an excerpt from a parish registry, C.W. Robinson's interpretation of family Pedigree 1589-1712 with detailed information about dates of births, deaths, and marriages. (Page 479-484)
    Entry in the "Churchwarden's Book" from the Parish of St. Helen about William Robinson.
  - Pedigree. (Page 485-486)
    Genealogy of Bishop Robinson as taken from church registries of Peter's Poor Church, London, Church of Great St. Helen, London, and Conyscliffe Parish, dating back to 1523.
  - Photograph. (Page 493-494)
    Monument to Bishop Robinson (d. 1599) in Great St. Helen's Church, London with inscription.
  - Monument inscription. (Page 496-497)
    C.W. Robinson's translation of the inscription on the monument to Bishop Robinson (d. 1599) and family in Great St. Helen's Church, London. Included are additional inscriptions found on the grave stones of Elizabeth Robinson (wife) and Sir Thomas Robinson (found in the Temple Church).
  - Copy of a map. (Page 499)
    Scaled drawing of the course of the Tees River, England(?) showing surrounding towns.
  - Pedigree. (Page 500-512)
    Description of Robinson family coat of arms, Motto and genealogy dating back to c. 1205 as constructed by Charles W. Robinson.
  - Memorandum, 7 January 1913.
    C.W. Robinson's viewing of a portrait of Bishop Robinson.
  - Coats of arms. (Page 516)
    C.W. Robinson's drawings and explanation of the Coats of Arms for William Robinson's pedigree (1633/34) and Bishop Robinson's pedigree (1712-23).
  - Cleasby window inscriptions. (Page 517)
    C.W. Robinson's copy of inscriptions on windows in Cleasby, England in memory of Bishop Robinson and Reverend John Robinson. Newspaper article from the Northeastern Gazette included.
  - Coat of arms, 18 August 1854. (Page 518)
    Colored sketch of the Coat of Arms granted to Sir John Beverley Robinson.
  - Photograph. (Page 519)
    Stained glass window of the Robinson Coat of Arms in Cleasby Church, England.
  - Letter from Cleasby Church, London, to C.W. Robinson(?), 17 February 1913. (Page unnumbered)
    Concerns the Cleasby Church window.
  - Coat of arms. (Page 520)
    Colored and black and white sketches of Robinson family crest.
  - Photograph. (Page 522-524)
    Photograph of Elizabeth Marshall Robinson, daughter of Conway Robinson with newspaper clipping dated 1909 announcing her death.
  - Notes on sources, January 1913.
    C.W. Robinson's notes on family pedigree research conducted through 1875 in Middlesex, Spotsylvania, Essex, Caroline, and King William counties, Virginia and the College of William and Mary with complete listing of relevant documents 8 November 1680 - 5 May 1792 as registered with Herald's College, London.
  - Copy of letters patent, 16 January 1692/3. (Page 579-583)
    Appointment of Christopher Robinson to the office of Secretary of the Colony of Virginia.
  - Notes on sources, 1876. (Page unnumbered)
    C.W. Robinson's notes from unnamed sources concerning William and John (1599) Robinson.
  - Article: "Notes and sketches" by G.A. Fothergill, 1908. (Page 585-594)
    Concerns Cleasby, England and Bishop Robinson. Includes photographs and drawings.
  - Copy of a will, 13 December 1731. (Page 595)
    Letitia Cornwallis (stepdaughter of Bishop Robinson) mentioning Bishop Robinson and "Cousin" Christopher at college.
  - Memorandum. (Page 596)
    Notes on the connection between Bishop Robinson and Letitia Cornwallis.
  - J.H. Coombe, Cleasby Vicar, Darlington, England, to C.W. Robinson(?), 29 March 1878. (Page 597-600)
    Letitia Cornwallis's will and supporting documents in the parish archives.
  - Copy of the will Letitia Cornwallis, 4 July 1739. (Page 601-618)
    Updated version of 1731 will giving money to various churches and charities and funds for the upkeep of Bishop Robinson's tomb and monument.
  - Copy of the will of Letitia Cornwallis, 31 January 1740. (Page 619-622)
    Third version of last will and testament adding directions for the sale of bedchamber furniture and curtains upon death.
  - Book appendix (Page 626-646)
    Section of text about C.W. Robinson's father concerning his relationship to Bishop John Robinson. Notes added in the margins by C.W.R.
  - Copy of a map, July 1787. (Page 647)
    Taken from a publication by the Virginia Historical Society, "Dinwiddie Papers", originally from Fry and Jefferson's map of Virginia, showing tidewater Virginia from Albermarle Sound to Baltimore. Notes by C.W. Robinson show Robinson family lands.
  - Pedigree, 1880. (Page 649)
    Robinson family tree of the Virginia Robinsons descending from John Robinson as compiled by C.W. Robinson.